[Music]
this video is sponsored by kite which is
a Python extension for vs code and many
other modern editors it offers
intelligent snippets and one-click
documentation using a program called
co-pilot that I'll actually be using in
this project to download kite on any
platform click on the link in the
description below what's going on guys
in this video we're gonna look at
scrapey which is a Python framework for
crawling websites and extracting data
and there's a bunch of reasons why you
might want to use something like this
for data analysis for data mining
information processing a lot of services
and websites give you data api's to work
with but not all of them do so there
might be a website where you you want
some data but there's no API available
so you can scrape the data yourself now
you have to keep in mind that there's a
lot of ethics and even legality that
goes into web scraping so if you're
using it in a professional sense for a
product or your company or something you
really want to look at that if you're
scraping data from another website you
want to look at their Terms and
Conditions and you know you want to be
ethical when you're dealing with web
scraping and that's really all I'm going
to say on the subject I'm not going to
tell you what to do and what not to do
so what we're going to do is scrape the
this right here this blog it's called
the scraping blog scraping hub blog and
I've seen this in a bunch of tutorial so
I figured it's fine for us to use in
this video and it's just a regular blog
and you can see that it has a bunch of
posts and then it has other pages of
posts so what I'd like to do is scrape
every single post and get the title so I
want the title the date and the author
and of course you could get other stuff
as well but those are the three things
that I really want to target and by the
end of this I want to be able to run a
command to scrape the website get all
that stuff and put it into a large JSON
file and of course you could do whatever
you like with it you could save it to a
database you could create a CSV you can
run it through what are called pipelines
and mess with the data after you extract
it there's a lot you can do but this is
kind of an inch
doctoral level course so we're gonna
create a script like I said to extract
to crawl and extract the data from the
blog and we're also going to be working
in the shell because scrapy has a shell
where we can directly run selectors and
run methods on those selectors to get
data all right so let's go ahead and
jump into vs code and I just I also have
my terminal opened down here I'm using
my integrated terminal and as with any
Python project we're gonna create a
virtual environment and I'm just going
to use the virtual env for that so if we
do Python 3 dash M V env and create a
folder called V env so that will be our
virtual environment and you can see
inside the bin folder there's an
activate script so we just want to call
that with source V and V slash bin slash
activate okay so they'll activate our
virtual environment and if you're
envious code you want to just command
shift P or ctrl shift P search for
Python select interpreter and just
select your virtual environment mine is
called V and V okay so now we should be
all set so I'm going to install scrapey
and we want to use pit for that or pipi
and V if you're using that so let's
install scrapy okay so once crepe is
installed we can go ahead and create a
project by saying scrapey start project
and then i'm just going to call this
we'll call it post scrape our post crawl
whatever you want to call it and then
we're just going to CD into post grade
and then let's take a look at the folder
up here that was created now there's
another folder called post scrape inside
of it along with this scrapy dot CFG
file and inside this folder we have a
file for middlewares for pipelines we
have something called item pipelines
where when you scrape when you crawl and
you extract the data you can do certain
things with it you can cleanse it you
can run validation on it different
things we're not going to get into that
that's that's more advanced and what I
want to do here all I want to do is
create a spider so inside the spiders
folder we're going to
create a new file called posts
underscore spider dot pi okay so this is
going to be our main file that we work
with and the first thing we're going to
do is import scrapie so that we can use
it and then we need to create a spider
class so let's say class we'll call it
posts spider and this needs to extend
scrapey dot spider now I want to take a
look at this this spider class and I'm
going to use kite to do that so the kite
extension gives us this docks link which
will actually open up copilot and it'll
show us everything that has to do with
this class okay so you can see all the
different members I just want to show
you a couple things so name is something
we're going to need it's a string to
identify the spider and it has to be
unique it has to be a string so let's go
ahead and add a name property here we'll
call this posts and then if we go back
to kite copilot we also want this start
urls which is a list or an array of URLs
that we want to crawl from so let's say
starts underscore URLs set that to a
list and we're gonna do HTTP blog dot
scraping hub comm and we can do slash
let's do /page /parent eyre page and put
it into a separate HTML file which isn't
very useful on its own aside from maybe
offline web viewing but it'll give you
an idea of how this works now we also
want a parse method so let's see right
here so parse which takes in a response
this is the default callback used by
scrapey to process download responses
when their requests don't specify a
callback so it's basically in charge of
the response in returning the scrape
data so let's go ahead and define parse
and we want to pass himself since it's a
method of this class and then it takes
in a response okay so the response is
basically the the data that we scrape
now in this case we're just going to
basically copy both of these pages and
create two new HTML files with the same
exact HTML so we're scraping the entire
page later on we're gonna target certain
certain elements of the page using
selectors and and put them into a JSON
file so I'm going to create a variable
called page and set that to response dot
URL so that will give us both of the
dealing with both of these URLs and I
just want to get the page number so in
this case one and two so we can use the
split method and we'll say we want to
split them by the slash and we want to
go one from the end so one slash from
the end and we should end up here at the
number so that should put either one or
two depending on whatever page or
scraping into this variable then we want
to set a file name and we're gonna set
it to posts - and then whatever the page
number so I'm gonna use my percent s by
my placeholder here dot HTML and then we
want to replace that with whatever the
page number now to actually create the
file we need to let's say with open and
that's going to take in the file name
and the right mode or the the file mode
which is going to be write binary as F
and then we're gonna as F and then we'll
say F dot right and we're gonna write to
the file the response dot body which is
the entire HTML all the HTML from both
of these pages will be put into these
files so let's save that and we can run
this with scrapey crawl and then
whatever we cut whatever the name is in
this case posts okay so whatever we put
here is what we want to put here
okay so we ran it now you can see over
here we have post - one and post - two
HTML so post - one is going to be this
so we just scraped the entire thing and
put it into this file and I can even
open this I'll open it with live server
and right on my localhost now we have
that entire page okay so I mean this is
it is good I guess for like offline
viewing or or for some reason if you
need to scrape an entire website so now
we're gonna take a break from from the
file for a little bit and we're gonna
work in the terminal because we're gonna
work with the shell just to kind of show
you how to select things how to use
methods and so on so the way we go into
our shell is we call scrapy shell and
then the the domain or the URL that we
want to crawl so in this case HTTP blog
dot scraping I can't even I can't
remember the URL scraping hub dot-com
okay so from here I'm just gonna clear
this stuff up with ctrl L so from here
we can we can use selectors CSS
selectors so we do that as we take that
response object which is the same as
this right here okay so later on we're
going to do this the same stuff we're
doing in here we're going to be doing in
our parse method so to use a CSS
selector we just do dot CSS and let's
say we want to get the title so what
this returns is something called the
selector list which represents a list of
selector objects that wrap around HTML
elements so you can see selector it has
the XPath which I'll talk about in a
little bit and data is going to be the
the actual element in this case the
title with the tags and the text inside
of it and if we look at the title of
this it's the scraping hub blog alright
so if we want to get just the element
then we can run response dot CSS title
and we can run a method on it such as
get
so what get does is it takes the first
match and returns it so you can see now
we just get the actual element now let's
say we want just the text because a lot
of the time you're not going to want the
actual tag so in that case we can just
add here a double colon title whoops
what I do
I'm sorry not title text let's run that
again it's a double colon text and that
gives us just the text okay so let's
let's experiment with this a little bit
so we have a we have h threes H 2's
paragraphs let's go ahead and say
response dot CSS and let's pass in h3
text dot get okay so what that does is
it gets us the text of the first h3 so
keep up to date with this scraping it's
this right here all right now if we want
the second one we can just go right here
and put in a set of brackets and put in
a 1 okay that'll give us a second if we
want the third we can put in 2 so it's
just like a list or an array and that's
the third one if we want to get all the
h3 s then we can get rid of this and we
can use the get all method so that gets
us all of the h3 texts and puts it into
a selector list if we want to include
the tags and attributes and all that
then we can just do that without text
and that will put you know the actual h3
ID classes whatever else is attached to
it ok so that's how we can select by tag
let's see what else we can also select
by like class or ID so if we open up
this and let's open up our google chrome
tools here so the the dev tools are they
definitely come in handy when you're
dealing with web scraping because you
need to know the structure of what
you're scraping so if we take a look at
a post right so this is post listing
wraps all of them and then each post has
a div with the class of post item
and in that post item we have a header
post header post content inside post
header we have an h2 with a link and
then the text for the heading okay then
we have a byline span with the class of
date that has an icon and a link and
then the date text so it's important to
know the structure it's it's like using
CSS or jQuery where you need to select
certain things so let's say we want to
get the whole post header so I could do
it's a response CSS and let's do dot
post - header so we can select by a
class and we could get all so that gives
us all the post headers or we could get
the first one you can do get like that
let's say we wanted to get the first
link in the post header we could just
add an A okay if we wanted to get just
the text of the first link could do that
if we want to get the second one I could
do that let's just the date alright so
pretty easy we can also use regular
expressions okay so there's a method
called re for regular expressions so if
I say response dot CSS and let's say we
want to get all the paragraph text and
let's say dot our e and in here we have
to format this with an our string like
this and let's say we want to get all
the instances of the word scraping
that'll do that if we want to get all
the instances of just anything that
starts with s so we can put in a word
character here and then + and that just
gives us everything that starts with a s
even if we wanted to get like right here
it says whether you are say we wanted to
get every word that has you the word you
in the middle of it we could go ahead
and do let's get rid of this and for our
regular expression we'll put a word
character and then the word you and then
another one so slashed up
U+ and it gives us every word that has
you in the middle so whether you are
actions you will when you should and so
on okay so you can put any regular
expression you can get data that way so
now what I want to do is take a look at
using XPath selectors so XPath is a it's
a language for selecting nodes in XML
documents and it can also be used with
HTML it's it's really difficult for me
actually it's kind of confusing but
these CSS selectors are kind of like
syntactic sugar for the XPath selectors
the XPath is what's happening under the
hood but you can use them directly like
say response dot XPath and let's say we
want to get all the h3 s we can do slash
slash h3 so if I do that then we get all
the h3 s if we wanted to get all the h3
to just the text we could do slash and
then txt with parentheses oh I'm sorry
we need to call a method so we can use
extract we can also use get all here as
well okay now with the chrome tools let
me just clear this up with our chrome
tools we can select we can get the XPath
for certain elements so let's say for
this author right here if I select that
this link and then I right-click and I
copy you can see there's an option to
copy the XPath so if I do that and then
I go back over here and I do response
dot XPath dots extract and then here I
put in some quotes and paste in what I
copied and run that I get the link with
the author okay and I can even pass in
here at the end slash text and just get
the text okay so you can use XPath
selectors as well and you can actually
target better with XPath there's more
things you can do it's just much more
difficult at least in my opinion
so let's see the next thing I want to do
is what I said I want to get the the
title the date and the author and we're
first going to do that in the terminal
here and we're going to do it with just
the first post and then I'll show you
how we can kind of loop through the
posts and get each each set of data so
let's set a variable so we can set
variables here and we're gonna say set
this post to response dot CSS okay so
these queries we can put them inside of
variables and we want to grab the div
with the class of post - item and the
reason for that is like I showed you
each post is wrapped in this post item
so I'm basically selecting the whole
post and putting it into a variable and
I want the I just want the first one so
we're gonna put 0 if I type post it's
going to show you the selector or the
selector list now to set the title
variable I'm going to set it to post dot
CSS so instead of using your spawn CSS
I'm actually using that post variable
and I'm gonna go into let's say we want
to go into the post header and from
there I'm going to go into the h2 and
then into the link and then I want the
text from that link so that's going to
give me the title right and I'm gonna
get first link the first one and we're
gonna use the get method so if I do
title that gives me just the text of the
the first post title if I want to do the
date let's see let's change this to date
now the date and stuff they I mean the
the structure of the HTML makes it
either more difficult or easier in this
case there's no class or anything on the
date if there was if there was I could
just do like a dot date or something
like that but in this case we're just
gonna grab from the header the second
link I'm sorry should be one so the
second link is actually the date so now
if I go ahead
I type date gives me the date okay for
the author same thing there's no class
directly on the link so we're gonna set
to the a third link in the post header
in the post so author there we go
alright so that's how we can do that
with just a single post now I'm going to
show you how we can loop through so
we're gonna say for post in response
response dot CSS and we want to grab say
div dot post - I eat them okay so we're
going to create a loop here so we're
looping through our posts and we want to
tap make sure you tab over here since
we're in the shell or else is just going
to end the line when you hit enter we
want to create a variable for each one
so title will take the post CSS and
inside here let's say post dots
I'm sorry not post on head our post -
header dot post - header and then from
there we're going to get the h2 from
there the link and we want the text I
want the first one and we want to get
okay so I'm going to enter and then tab
over and then let's add the date and
we're gonna say post start CSS
post header link we want the second link
this time we want to get it and then we
want the author so that'll be post
header link text we want the third one
and we want to get it and then for the
last line I'm gonna go ahead and print
and I want to print out a dictionary so
I'm going to use the the D ICT function
here and then pass in title is going to
be the title variable date will be the
date variable and the author will be the
author variable okay so we'll run that
and you can see that now we have a bunch
of dictionaries that have the title the
date and the author so we've looped
through all the posts and outputted that
data so we now what we want to do is
kind of the same thing but we want to do
it within our file and we want to create
a JSON file not just print it out so now
I think we're pretty much done here yeah
let's just let's get out of this so I'll
just go ahead and quit so let's go back
into our file and I'm gonna get rid of
this second one here and I'm just going
to use the route URL because again I'm
going to show you how we can go through
all the pages without having to actually
manually add them so we want that there
and then in the parse we don't need any
of this we're not just gonna copy the
pages like we did before we want to loop
through like I just showed you we're
gonna say for post in response dot CSS
so we use these selectors the same way
as we did in the shell div dot post item
okay so we want to loop through the post
and then we need to yield so since we're
in this file we're going to yield a
dictionary with the title and that's
going to come from post dot CSS
ultimately it's going to be it's going
to be the post header h2 link text first
one dot get okay and then I'm just gonna
copy that down twice and then this one
is gonna be one we don't need the h2
here or here and this will be too so
pretty much the same thing we did yeah
so that should do it we just need to
change the keys so this one here will be
the date because the date is the second
link and then the author is the third
link and again this could be a class if
there was an actual class on the link or
an ID or something all right so just
doing that I think we should be good so
I'm gonna save and then I'm gonna go
down here and if I just run scrapy crawl
and then post all it's gonna do really
is just show me down here in the console
you can see the data the title and so on
so we want to actually put this into a
JSON file so we just want to add on to
this the output flag and say post dot
jason and you can do that jl format
which is a jason list you can do CSV you
can do all kinds of stuff we're gonna do
a JSON file and check it out so now we
have adjacent array with all of the
posts but notice it's only on the first
page okay so we have all the posts on
the first page so now I'm going to show
you how we can actually follow links and
scrape data from other pages so if we go
back here and we go down to the
pagination so this right here older
posts and we take a look
at that so this it's this is going to be
pretty easy because this link has a
class of next post link right so
remember that and then it has an H an
href attribute that goes to the next
page that we want to scrape so back here
we want to go on the same level as our
for loop here and create a next page
variable and we're going to set that to
response dot CSS and remember it's a
link with a class of next what was it
next post link but we want the actual
attribute so we can do this we can do
double : attribute and we want to get
whatever's in the href okay I should I
could have showed you this in the shell
as well and then get so that'll give us
the actual link to the next page now we
want to make sure that there is a next
page so let's say if if next page is is
not none because if there is no next
page if that link doesn't exist it's
gonna be none so we want to say if it's
not none then let's say next page is
gonna equal response dot and then
there's a method called URL join and we
want to join in the next page okay so
basically we're scraping the next page
as well and then the last thing we have
to do is just call yield scrape beat dot
request and that takes in our next page
and a callback and in this case it's
going to be our parse because we want to
run our parse again so we'll set
callback equal to our self dot parse
method so I'm going to save this and now
what should happen is it should scrape
the entire site so I'm going to delete
this JSON file that we just created and
I'm gonna run this again so output post
Jason and it's going to take a little
longer because there's more data to go
through
so right now it's just scraping the
entire blog and if I go to my post Jason
so there's now there's tons more data
because it went through every single
page and it took the title the date and
the author alright so I mean that's
pretty much it there's a lot more you
can do that's much more advanced but I
think that just for the amount of code
that we wrote here what is this it's 21
lines counting the the spaces here so
you know less than 20 lines of code and
we're able to scrape an entire website
and get certain pieces of data I don't
know how useful some blog fields are but
if you go to like an e-commerce site for
a certain category maybe you want to
have a list of all the products or
something like that
scrapy is really good for for stuff like
that so hopefully you learned something
here and you enjoyed it and that's it I
will see you in the next video